Guide to the John E. Fleming Papers, 1962-2013 RL.11014
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John E. Fleming papers
1961-2014
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Fleming, John
RL.11014
57 Linear Feet
Dr. John E. Fleming served as director of the National Afro-American Museum and Cultural Center in Wilberforce, Ohio, from 1988-1998 and served on numerous boards and committees to develop and plan museums and exhibits focused on African American history. His papers reflect his career as a historian of African American history and as a museum administrator in museums throughout the United States. Collection acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Collection Overview
The collection includes Fleming's personal files, administrative materials, and collected documents from his education and professional life as a professor and museum administrator. Files have been arranged into series: Writings, Organizational Files, Museum Leadership, Printed Materials and Research, Asa Spaulding Project, Education, Personal, and Correspondence. The bulk of the collection is held in the Organizational Files and Museum Leadership series.
The Organizational Files Series contains a large subseries of Fleming's Consulting Work, as well as files from Fleming's membership and service to groups like ASALH, AAAM, Sigma Pi Phi, and other civic or professional organizations. This series also includes Fleming's board work with Berea College, the Ohio Humanities Council, the American Civil War Center, and other historically-minded groups.
The Museum Leadership Series is arranged by museum; Fleming served as director or in some executive capacity with each of the museums in this series. Most subseries include his correspondence, planning and design materials, exhibition materials, and other documents accounting for the early operations of the museums. Also included in this series are materials from the America I Am exhibit, which Fleming produced. Two of the subseries are restricted: the International African American Museum subseries is closed until 2018, and the Mississippi Civil Rights Museum is closed until 2017.
The rest of the collection's series are relatively smaller, in terms of volume. The Writings Series includes Fleming's speeches and publications; files are arranged by format and then alphabetically by title. Printed Materials and Research include his clippings, articles, and publications he kept as reference materials for his museum work and academic research. The Asa Spaulding Project includes oral history notes, transcripts, and cassette tapes from Fleming's work as a research assistant for Spaulding's autobiography. The Education Series includes coursework and notes from his own college and graduate courses, as well as files from his teaching at Howard University following his graduation. The Personal Series contains an assortment of materials, including job searches, clippings about him and his family, and other ephemera. Finally, Fleming's Correspondence Series includes both personal and professional communications, which are arranged in a loose chronological order by year.
Provenance
The John Fleming Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2013.
Historical note
John E. Fleming (1944- ) is originally from Morganton, N.C., and graduated from Berea College in 1966. He served for two years in the Peace Corps in Malawi, and then attended Howard University, earning a Ph.D. in History. In the 1970s, he worked with Howard's Institute for the Study of Educational Policy and also as a professor in the History Dept. Fleming was the founding director of the National Afro-American Museum and Cultural Center in Cincinnati, and also served as director of the National Underground Railroad Freedom Center in Wilberforce, Ohio. Fleming later worked as Vice President of Museums at the Cincinnal Museum Center; served as the executive producer for Tavis Smiley's America I Am: The African American Imprint exhibit, which toured nationwide; and was director or consultant for several other museums and historic sites, including the International African American Museum, the Mississippi Civil Rights Museum, and the National African American Museum. Fleming has authored several books on African American history and education, and has also published a novel, A Summer Remembered. He is a past president of the Association for the Study of African American Life and History, the Ohio Museums Association, and the Association of African American Museums.
African Americans -- Civil rights -- History; African Americans -- History; Museums -- Social aspects -- United States; African Americans -- Museums; Peace Corps (U.S.); Museums -- Management; Museums -- Administration; Historical museums; Ohio Humanities Council; National Underground Railroad Freedom Center (Cincinnati, Ohio); National African American Museum (U.S.); National Afro-American Museum and Cultural Center; International African American Museum (Charleston, S.C.); Smiley, Tavis; Cincinnati Museum Center; Association for the Study of Afro-American Life and History; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture; Spaulding, Asa T. (Asa Timothy), 1902-1990; Berea College; Ohio Historical Society
- Writings, 1970s-2010s; 2
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes drafts and published versions of Fleming's speeches, journal articles, essays, and books. Speeches range from personal tributes to academic lectures, and are arranged alphabetically by title. Dates and any additional information are included when known. Fleming's Academic Writings include his dissertation and subsequent versions of his research on Burke County, N.C., as well as research and articles on affirmative action, African American culture and history, and museum leadership. The Fiction Writings contains drafts of A Summer Remembered, a partly-autobiographical novel published by Fleming.
  - Speeches, 1977-2010; 1
    - A Dream Unfulfilled, MLK Celebration, Clark St Community College, 1991 Jan 17 (Box 1)
    - A. Phillip Randolph, MLK Center Speech, undated (Box 1)
    - A Summer Remembered, undated (Box 1)
    - A Summer Remembered, Appalachian Studies Association Conference, 2006 (Box 1)
    - AAM Award, undated (Box 1)
    - Affirmative Action and Black Higher Education at Conference for Lilly Endowment Grantees for Improvement of Instruction in the Social Sciences, 1979 June 3 (Box 1)
    - Affirmative Action for Blacks in Higher Education, American Association for Affirmative Action, 1977 May 10 (Box 1)
    - Affirmative Action for Blacks in Higher Education: A Historical Perspective, AHA, 1979 Dec 30 (Box 1)
    - Affirmative Action and the Distribution of Black Faculty in Institutions of Higher Education, Wayne State University, 1980 Sept 10 (Box 1)
    - Affirmative Action and the Higher Education Community: A Perspective on Black Employment and Government Policy, Howard University, 1980 Apr 11 (Box 1)
    - Affirmative Action Implications of the Distribution of Black Faculty and Higher Education, American Association for Affirmative Action Conference, 1980 Apr 30 (Box 1)
    - Affirmative Action and the Reversal of Discrimination, undated (Box 1)
    - African Americans, Affirmative Action and Higher Education, Xenia, Ohio, 1996 Oct 6 (Box 1)
    - African Americans in Appalachia, Berea College symposium, 1989 (Box 1)
    - African American Education During Slavery, undated (Box 1)
    - The African American Experience in Ohio, 1850-1920, Statehouse, 1996 July (Box 1)
    - African American Institutions: Keepers of Our Cultural Heritage, Alliance, Ohio, 1993 Feb 10 (Box 1)
    - African American Museums and Fundraising Resources in the Black Business Community, undated (Box 1)
    - African American Museums, History and the American Ideal, ASALH, 1996 Sept 21 (Box 1)
    - African American Museums, History and the American Ideal, ASALH, undated (Box 1)
    - African American Philanthropy: Plugging in Where You Can, Springfield Foundations African American Community Family of Funds, 2007 Feb 28 (Box 1)
    - African Americans in 19th Century Ohio, Toledo, Ohio, 2004 Oct 16 (Box 1)
    - Afro-American History, A Retrospective Corps of Engineers, WV, 1983 Feb 23 and undated (Box 1)
    - Afro-American History: The Foundation for New Directions in Affirmative Action, Department of Transportation, 1979 Feb 21 (Box 1)
    - Afro-American Institutions: Historical Strengths for Our Future Survival, Lee Chapel A.M.E. Church, Cincinnati, Ohio, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Afro-American Institutions: Historical Strengths for Our Future Survival, Advent Community Church, Columbus, Ohio, 1985 Feb 10 (Box 1)
    - Afro-American Institutions: Historical Strengths for Our Future Survival, Morehouse College, 1986 Feb 1 (Box 1)
    - Afro-American Institutions: Historical Strengths for Our Future Survival, Stewart Memorial Christian Episcopal Church, Columbus, Ohio, 1987 Feb (Box 1)
    - Afro-American Institutions: Historical Strengths for our Future Survival, Miami University, 1990 Feb 8 (Box 1)
    - Afro-American Museums in the 1980s: The Transmission of Cultural Values, Knoxville, TN, undated (Box 1)
    - The Aftermath of Bakke, Department of Agriculture, 1978 Dec 5 (Box 1)
    - To Alpha Kappa Alpha, Cincinnati Museum Center, undated (Box 1)
    - America I Am, The African American Imprint at Berea College, 2010 Feb 25 (Box 1)
    - America I Am, African American Imprint on America for Walmart Executives, undated (Box 1)
    - Are We Bridging the Racial Divide? Washington, D.C., 2008 Sept 25 (Box 1)
    - Art Criticism from a Lay, Black Perspective, undated (Box 1)
    - The Art of Reinvention: A Metaphor for African American Museums, undated (Box 1)
    - Bakke, Affirmative Action and the Future, undated (Box 1)
    - The Bakke Decision and Higher Education, American Association of Personnel Administrators, 1979 Apr 8 (Box 1)
    - Bakke and Higher Education: Future Implications for Affirmative Action, undated (Box 1)
    - Berea Human Rights Advocates, Berea College, undated (Box 1)
    - Black Access to Higher Education: Faculty and Students, University of MD, 1981 Feb 4 (Box 1)
    - Black Family Speech Research, 1988 Jun 12 (Box 1)
    - Black History Month, undated (Box 1)
    - Black History Month, Library of Congress, 2007 Feb 8 (Box 1)
    - Black Institutions and the Transmission of Cultural Values, Dayton, Ohio, undated (Box 1)
    - Blacks, Affirmative Action and History, undated (Box 1)
    - Blacks and Higher Education: Past, Present and Future, Education Opportunity Center, 1978 Oct 11 (Box 1)
    - Building African American Collections, Earlham College, 1995 Feb 1 (Box 1)
    - Building African American Collections: If You Don't, Who Will?, Canton, Ohio, 1993 Nov 20 (Box 1)
    - The Case for Affirmative Action for Blacks in Higher Education, 1979 Apr 26 (Box 2)
    - Carter G. Woodson and the Origins of Multi-Culturalism, 2008 Feb 28 (Box 2)
    - Cincinnati's Rich African American History, undated (Box 2)
    - The Civil Rights Movement and African American Education, 1994 Jan 13 (Box 2)
    - The Civil Rights Movement and African American Education, undated (Box 2)
    - CMC Youth Program, Columbia, SC, 2006 Feb 14 (Box 2)
    - Climbing Jacob's Ladder, Hayes Museum, 1997 July 27 (Box 2)
    - Color in Freedom, University of Maryland, 2008 Nov 1 (Box 2)
    - Comments on Dan Hurley, undated (Box 2)
    - Consultants and the National Afro-American Museum, Wright State University, 1989 June 5 (Box 2)
    - Creating and Preserving African-American Collections, Columbus, Ohio, 1993 June 18 (Box 2)
    - Defining the Fifties, undated (Box 2)
    - Democratizing our Profession, AASLH Conference, 1991 Aug 23 (Box 2)
    - Democratizing our Profession, Dearborn, Michigan, 1991 Aug 23 (Box 2)
    - Documenting the African American Experience: A Personal Journey, Ohio University, 2006 Oct 11 (Box 2)
    - The Dream - Not to be Forgotten, Columbus, OH (The Federal Community Annual Martin Luther King, Jr. Birthday Celebration), 1997 Jan 15 (Box 2)
    - Educating American: Black Colleges: Historical Strengths & Crises, Cincinnati, Ohio, 1991 Feb 11 (Box 2)
    - The Education of Black People: An American Paradox, Morgan State University, 1980 Feb 7 (Box 2)
    - Empowering Afro-American Institutions: Historical Strengths for our Future Survival, Yellow Springs, Ohio (Central Chapel A.M.E.), 1994 Feb 13 (Box 2)
    - Eulogy for Hellen O'Neal-McCray, Wilberforce, Ohio (St. Paul Catholic Church), 2010 Mar 6 (Box 2)
    - Everybody Can Be Great, Because Everybody Can Serve, undated (Box 2)
    - The Freedom Center's Programs, undated (Box 2)
    - From Dred Scott, to Plessy to Brown and Beyond: An Historical Overview, Wilberforce, Ohio, 2004 May 17 (Box 2)
    - From Slavery to Freedom: Africans in the Americas, Carlisle, PA, 2007 Feb 25 (Box 2)
    - Future Directions for Black Historians, undated (Box 2)
    - The History of Afro-American Museums and the Wilberforce Experience, Cincinnati, Ohio, 1993 Feb 24 (Box 2)
    - History and the Black Community, undated (Box 2)
    - History of Historically Black Colleges and University, undated (Box 2)
    - The Impact of Affirmative Action on Black Males in Higher Education, Institute for Urban Affairs Research Conference, 1979 Nov 2 (Box 2)
    - The Impact of Civil Rights and American Museums, American Association of Museums, 2000 May 18 (Box 2)
    - The Impact of the Civil Rights Movement on African American Education, Convocation at Muskingum College, 1994 Jan 13 (Box 2)
    - Inequality of Opportunity: The Case for Color-Conscious Remedies, International Association of Official Human Rights Agencies, 1979 July 9 (Box 2)
    - Interpretation and Cultural Tourism, undated (Box 2)
    - John Wilson Fleming, undated (Box 2)
    - Legacy of the Civil War, undated (Box 2)
    - The Legacy of Rayford Logan, Howard University, 2008 Feb 20 (Box 2)
    - The Legacy of Slavery and the Struggle for Higher Education, The Chester W. Gregory, Sr. Inaugural Colloquium, 2007 Apr 24 (Box 2)
    - Modern Business Management Techniques as Applied to Non-Profit Organization, Museum Trustee Association Spring Conference, 1991 May 18 (Box 2)
    - Museum History and the Importance of Values, undated (Box 2)
    - The NAAMCC and Thoughts on Multiculturalism, Doris L. Allen Minority Caucus, 1991 Dec 6 (Box 2)
    - The National Underground Railroad Freedom Center: A New Type of Museum for the 21st Century, undated (Box 2)
    - The National Underground Railroad Freedom Center and Berea College, 2006 (Box 2)
    - The Need for Black Institutions in the 1980s: A Historical Perspective, Beck Cultural Exchange Center, Knoxville, Tennessee, undated (Box 2)
    - NC Museum of History Presentation, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Ohio Black History Month, undated (Box 2)
    - Ohio Capitol dedication, 1996 July 9 (Box 2)
    - Olive Hill Class of 1962 Reunion, Winston Salem, 2007 (Box 2)
    - Peace Corps Presentation at Hamilton County Library, 2001 Sept 7 (Box 2)
    - The Perpetuations of the "Slave Mentality" in the Post-War Education of Blacks, undated (Box 2)
    - Post Colonial African American Achievements, undated (Box 2)
    - Preserving Our Heritage: A Historical Perspective, Toledo, 2004 Oct. 16 (Box 2)
    - Preserving Our Heritage Through Cultural Institutions, Rossville Museum and Cultural Center, 1984 June 16 (Box 2)
    - The Quest for Black Citizenship in the Americas, undated (Box 2)
    - Reflections on a Career in Public History, undated (Box 2)
    - Retirement Remarks, undated (Box 2)
    - Robert E. Lee: Symbol, Myth, and Reality: Opening Remarks, Richmond, 2002 Feb 22 (Box 2)
    - Schooled and Unschooled Biblican Exegetes in the African-American Religious Experience, 1865-1900, undated (Box 2)
    - The Second Reconstruction Under Attack, undated (Box 2)
    - Slavery and Public History, Carlisle, PA, undated (Box 3)
    - Slavery and Public History, Yale, undated (Box 3)
    - Starting a Museum: The Experience of the National Afro-American Museum and Cultural Center Project, undated (Box 3)
    - Trends and Challenges in American Museums, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Values Presentation, undated (Box 3)
    - Wings over Jordan, Wilberforce, Ohio, 1997 Sept 21 (Box 3)
    - What is (and can be) the role of a cultural institution in promoting values like "racial reconciliation"?, Dialogue II conference, Vancouver, 1999 Aug (Box 3)
    - What the Negro Wants from Business and Industry, undated (Box 3)
    - What's in a Name? Multiculturalism in the 1990s, PALS Foundation forum, 1996 Oct 6 (Box 3)
    - Why Affirmative Action for Blacks in Higher Education, undated (Box 3)
    - Woodson Center Dedication, Berea College, 2003 Feb 21-23 (Box 3)
    - Untitled Speeche delivered at Mt. Zion Methodist Church, Annual Men's Day, Cincinnati, OH, 1999 May 23 (Box 3)
    - Untitled Speeches, undated (Box 3)
    - Untitled talk for St. Stephen's Episcopal Church, Morganton, NC, 1999 Oct 3 (Box 3)
  - Academic Writings, 1
    - Book Reviews by John Fleming, 1970s-1980s (Box 3)
    - Letters to the editor, 1970s-1990s (Box 3)
    - Bakke: "A Historical Perspective," New Directions, 1977 (Box 3)
    - "A State/Federal Partnership Yields a New Museum" in Org. Your Museum: The Essentials, undated (Box 3)
    - African American Material Culture Book proposals, 1989-1991 (Box 3)
    - "African-American Museums, History and the American Ideal," Journal of American Hist., 1994 (Box 3)
    - "Affirmative Action: the Reversal of Discrimination," ISEP Monitor, 1977 Dec (Box 3)
    - "An Appalachian Afro-American Family," Appalachian Heritage, Fall 1991 (Box 3)
    - The Art of Reinvention: A Metaphor for African American Museums, in International Review of African American Art, 2006-2007 (Box 3)
    - Comments on "Beulah Land", undated (Box 3)
    - Black College Project (Outline), undated (Box 3)
    - Black Freedom in a White Society: The Freedmen in Burke Co., NC After the Civil War, 1865-1868, 1978 and undated (Box 3)
    - Black Males in Higher Education, undated (Box 3)
    - "Blacks in southern Appalachia after emancipation: a social history" grant proposals, 1979 and undated (Box 3)
    - "Blacks in Higher Education to 1954: A Historical Overview," article, 1979 (Box 3)
    - "Blacks, Employment, and Racial Exclusion and Discrimination, A Bibliography", undated (Box 3)
    - "Burke had many U.S. post offices" Morganton News Herald, 1975 (Box 3)
    - The Case for Affirmative Action for Blacks in Higher Education, Permissions (Box 3)
    - The Case for Affirmative Action for Blacks in Higher Education, published version, 1978 (Box 3)
    - The Case for Affirmative Action for Blacks in Higher Education, Reviews, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
    - Cincinnati's Rich African American History, prepared for Who's Who, 2005 (Box 3)
    - Dictionary of American Negro Biography entries: Alexander Walters, George W. Ellis, Ernest Lyon, 1975 (Box 3)
    - "Dr. Margaret T. Burroughs: Artist, Teacher, Administrator…," Public Historian, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Educating America: Black Universities and Colleges: Strengths and Crises, undated (Box 3)
    - "Emancipation" article, HBO (?), undated (Box 3)
    - "Faculty Distribution in Higher Education," New Directions, 1980 (Box 3)
    - The Lengthening Shadow of Slavery - previous title, "Shadows of Slavery" draft, undated (Box 3)
    - The Lengthening Shadow of Slavery, master copy, 1976 (Box 3)
    - The Lengthening Shadow of Slavery Reviews, press, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Lillian Fleming Tapp, undated (Box 3)
    - My Brush with the Legacy of Roots Author Alex Haley, NAAMCC Newsletter, 1993 (Box 3)
    - The Need for Affirmative Action for Blacks in Higher Education: A Historical Perspective, undated (Box 3)
    - Neoconservatism: The Road to and from Bakke, undated (Box 3)
    - Out of Bondage: The Adjustment of Burke County Negroes after the Civil War 1865-1890, Dissertation draft, 1974; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Out of Bondage: The Adjustment of Burke County Negroes after the Civil War 1865-1890, Dissertation final version, 1974 (Box 4)
    - The Post-Civil War Adjustment of Blacks in Burke County, North Carolina, 1979 (Box 4)
    - "Preserving a Legacy," History News, 1993 (Box 4)
    - "Preserving Black Heritage," Yellow Springs News, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Reflections on a Career in the Humanities, published in Pathways, 2008 (Box 4)
    - "Slavery, Civil War, and Reconstruction: A Study of Black Women in Microcosm," Negro History Bulletin, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Some Reasons Why Marcus Garvey's Back-to-Africa Movement Failed, Draft, 1972 (Box 4)
    - The Stono River Rebellion, 1739, Draft and research, 1973 (Box 4)
    - "Taking Stock of Afro-American Material Culture," History News, 1985 Feb (Box 4)
    - WEB DuBois and Alpha Phi Alpha, Draft, undated (Box 4)
    - What the Negro Wants from Business and Industry, Chapter draft and correspondence, 1978 (Box 4)
    - William Monroe Trotter, A Sketch of a Black Dissenter, undated (Box 4)
    - Unlabelled and untitled drafts and edits, undated (Box 4)
  - Fiction Writings, 2
    - Me and Ike, Draft, 2001 (Box 4)
      Scope and Contents note
      Earlier title of A Summer Remembered
    - Me and Ike, Draft, undated; 3 folders (Box 4)
      Two versions; earlier title of A Summer Remembered.
    - Notes for Me and Ike, undated (Box 4)
    - A Summer Remembered, Draft and comments, 2001 (Box 4)
    - A Summer Remembered, Proof pages, undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - A Summer Remembered, Agent search, 2003-2004 (Box 4)
    - A Summer Remembered, Presentations and promotions, 2005-2007; 4 folders (Box 4)
      Includes correspondence with Planned Television Arts, Fleming's agency.
- Organizational Files, 1963-2013
  Fleming's wide range of service on various boards, professional organizations, and commissions are documented in this series. The Consulting subseries includes assorted projects and early employment records, as well as ephemera from his Peace Corps Service. The rest of the subseries represent specific groups Fleming worked with between the 1980s and the 2010s.
  - Consulting, Early Professional Work, Professional Affiliations, and Community Service, 1960s-2010s; 3
    This subseries includes Fleming's work as a consultant for various African American history museums or organizations, as well as his membership and service in various community, fraternal, and professional groups. Materials are arranged alphabetically by organization, group, or project. Of note in this subseries are files related to Fleming's early professional career, including the Peace Corps, Afro-American Bicentennial Corporation, and Youth Pride, Inc., as well as files documenting his participation in groups like Sigma Phi Pi, Leadership Cincinnati, and Alpha Phi Alpha.
    - Abell Foundation, Baltimore, 1987 (Box 5)
      Consulting work.
    - African American Cultural Center, Pittsburgh, 2005 (Box 5)
    - African American Museum of Delaware, 2002; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Afro-American Bicentennial Corportation, 1972-1974; 4 folders (Box 5)
      Contracts, correspondence, and research re: Sojourner Truth, Marcus Garvey, WEB DuBois sites, and Denmark Vesey.
    - Afro-American Bicentennial Corportation, 1972-1974; 2 folders (Box 38)
      Oversized Marcus Garvey research
    - Afro-American Cultural Center, Charlotte, 2005 (Box 5)
    - Afro-American Genealogical and Historical Society, 1977-1979 (Box 5)
    - Alpha Phi Alpha, Chi Lambda Chapter, 1980s-1990s; 3 folders (Box 5)
      Chapter correspondence, meeting minutes, events, other activities.
    - Alpha Phi Alpha, 1980s-1990s (Box 5)
      Miscellaneous organization pamphlets and publications.
    - American Anthropological Association, 2005 (Box 5)